So yeah the suta for today it's angutra
nikica 539 that uh we have translated as cannot
539 that uh we have translated as cannot
endure. So it starts by um the Buddha
addressing the the bicus and giving the
comparison with the bull elephant that
is not worthy and worthy of a king.
Obviously the sut is not very very long
or complex but it does raise some
interesting points about the whole um
nature of samadi and where the samadei
comes from uh to put it that way. So the
the examples the Buddha gives it starts
by saying how the royal bull elephant
cannot endure
sights and um it is when a royal bull
elephant gone to the battle gone to the
battle falters and founders at the sight
of a division of elephants of cavalry of
chariots of infantry it doesn't stay
firm and fails to plunge into a battle
that's how a royal bull elephant cannot
endure sights how can that royal bull elephant
sights how can that royal bull elephant
not endure sounds and then goes the same
it's when it's gone to the battle it
flinches palters at the sound of
division of elephants uh the thunder of
drums the kettle drums the horns
basically gets scared it doesn't stay
firm fails to plunge into the
battle how is the royal bull elephant
how can the royal bull elephant not
endure smells says it is when a royal
bull elephant gone to the battle of all
his fallen founders when it smells the
order of the feces urine of the battle
hardened pedigree royal bull elephants
it doesn't stay
firm how cannot endure tastes and it
goes the same when it's basically during
the battle it misses a meal grass water
misses two three four five meals uh it
doesn't stay firm gives in the mind gets
overwhelmed how is the royal bull
elephant cannot endure touches it's when
he's prodded by the arrows uh spears um
gets hit cannot stay firm. So it cannot
remain unmoved. So elephant that has not been
unmoved. So elephant that has not been
trained in remaining unmoved in those
five ways is the elephant that's uh not
worthy of a king, not worthy of a um
well not worthy to go into battle.
So in the same way au with five
qualities is not worthy of offerings
dedicated to gods not worthy of
hospitality not worthy of religious
donation or worthy of veneration with
joint palms and it's not the supreme
field of merit for the
world. What five when a beu cannot
endure sight sounds smell taste and
touches. Um so now when it comes to the
beu um the suda says that beu cannot
endure sights when seeing a sight with their
sights when seeing a sight with their
eyes he is aroused by a desirable sight
he's not able to compose the
mind as a result of that that's how
cannot endure
sights how is it that au cannot endure
sounds when a biku hearing a sound with
their ears is aroused by a desirable
sound. Thus, he cannot compose the mind.
So, the lack of composure is the result
of that arousal pretty
much. Um, same goes for the smells. When
a smell, when smelling an order with the
nose is aroused by a desirable smell,
he's not able to compose the
mind. Cannot end your tastes. It's when
a bigu tasting a flavor is aroused by
desirable tastes. and cannot endure
touches. It's when a bigu feeling
attached with the body is aroused by
desirable touch and thus he cannot
compose his mind. That's how big cannot
end your touches.
So, so the point here is some of you uh
noticed um like when I um when I sent that email
um like when I um when I sent that email
out is that when it came to the
comparison with the
elephant, the whole thing was about
enduring battle,
discomfort, fear, threat, faltering ing and
fear, threat, faltering ing and
flinching in face of all of those uh
prospects. But then when it came to the
comparisons with uh for the bikus, it
talks about pleasures. It doesn't talk
about enduring pains and so on. And
uh that's because the entire um training
of the mind, training of the elephant,
training of the battle, it's on the
level of uh where the desires are. So
generally when an unpleasant feeling
touches you, um you might have a desire
to um get rid of it. You might have a
desire against it, but that desire is
not as um deeply rooted to put it that
way as a sensual desire. So it's not a
desire that will be uh pertaining to a
lot kind of more um say uh existential
prospects of engaging with the world on
account of your desire. And it's also
something that even for some mundane
reasons you can convince yourself to
endure. Like if you find a good reason,
you will endure hardship, you will
endure hunger, you will endure
discomfort. But it's hard to find a good
reason to endure saying no to your
desires. So it's not accidental that this is not
So it's not accidental that this is not
mentioned because more or less as I said
pretty much anybody can master up
determination or or a sense of will uh
if motivation to to put up with
aesthetic practice or with this or with
that. Uh but nobody will accidentally be
practicing sense restraint. Nobody will
accidentally choose to stick to saying
no to their to their senses repeatedly
and so on. So that's why the
battleground and that whole thing
revolves pretty much on the level of
where your desires are where that
pressure is felt. But so the point is
that if somebody is not
trained in enduring these five there is
no samadei there is no mental
composure. Um, of course, um, you know,
it doesn't mean you should you should
not try to be composed, but you have to
recognize that if you are still driven
and taking for granted the desire that
comes that pressures you on a kind of
sight, sound, smell, taste, touches, you
are disqualifying yourself from the
establishment of samadei.
So it's not it's not an accident that
the whole training of an unfaltering
mind a non-flinching mind comes through
training of the uh in regard to desire
regarding sight, sounds, smell, taste
and touches. So the suta obviously gives
touches. So the suta obviously gives
this comparison then continues and says
okay so how is then the royal bull
elephant worthy of the king and he says
well it's worthy because he can endure
the sights.
um he doesn't falter at the sights of an
infantry division of elephants the
battle he doesn't get scared same goes
for sounds goes for smells same goes for
tastes touches and such elephant is
worthy of a
king so then in the same way a bicu is
worthy of offerings if he trains in
regard to sight sound smell taste
touches but again not trains blindly
through like I don't know um a setting
practice of avoiding sights, avoiding
sounds, uh avoiding tastes, eating only
once every six weeks or something
because that's the training. No, no.
Training in regard to
desire, the prospect of desire that
arises on account of a taste, on account
of a
sight. So it's not as easy as just just
avoid avoid sight, sound, smell, taste,
touches. Of course in the beginning you
have to start simply through withdrawing
yourself truly like overwhelming amount
of sight sounds melt touches so that you
can train in regard to the desire that
would be provoked by those and same if
we stick to the example of the elephant
you would not be immediately throwing a
wild untamed untrained elephant into the
battle like obviously it will it will it
will run away and it won't fight. Um but
sometimes people kind of um confuse or
take too far the recognition that okay
so I do have to avoid sight sounds me
smell taste touches to some extent thus
I will adopt the view that those must be
avoided and the more I avoid them the
better the closer to um nibbana or some
sort of freedom from craving I'm getting
but that's not correct so you need to
avoid it relatively speaking avoid the
obvious unh wholesome ones that simply
have no no practical value or any
benefit whatsoever. Uh but then you actually
whatsoever. Uh but then you actually
have to be training the mind in regard
to those, not just be saying no to them.
So that's kind of the main the main gist
of the suta. So I did ask what
constitutes enduring of sights, sounds,
smell, taste, and tastes and touches.
You're not enduring
um these battlegrounds to put it that
way. You're not enduring by just blindly
saying no or trying to deny the fact
that your eyes see and get attracted to
sights. Your ears hear and prefer
sounds, your nose like smells and so on.
Um it's like to be able to contain them,
you need to be able to not act out of
them. So when I when I keep talking
about enduring things on the right
level, that's what the right level is.
Basically enduring things on the right
level means containing things on the
right
level. And when you when you when you
contain them, that's where that whole uh
them, that's where that whole uh
training develops. So it's like how
would you train an elephant that's not
used to the the battle drums, the the
smell of feces? Well, by exposing it to
it in a controlled manner. So they get
used to so that it can overcome its
inherent tendency to flinch and look
away and run away. The the next thing I
asked was like why is the six sense the
mind uh omitted? The first reason is
because by training the five senses you
are training the mind you are developing
that but the second reason is you will
not be able to say not act out of the
delight towards phenomena towards images
towards ideas
uh if you haven't been already
sufficiently trained in regard to sight
sounds smell taste and
touches. So you know all those talks
when we talk about not allowing things
the center stage um they do kind of
pertain to that later stage of
development obviously you should be
considering it and aiming for it but the
the the the the fact is that
unless you are an elephant that doesn't
flinch in face of sight sound smell
taste and touches there is no training
in regard to the images in the mind it's
simply you're not seeing it. So in order
for that to be really like clearly
outlined um defined you know in the in the
um defined you know in the in the
peripheral and so on that mind and
images this training the training of the
battleground needs to be cultivated for
as long as it takes.
Um so that kind of leads to the next
question which is like how does the
battleground similly translate to your
everyday life? Where is the
battleground? Where do you look for the
battleground? Do you just go and start
saying no to random things to experience
the battleground or do you do you sort
of need to fabricate it in your mind?
But I think by now obviously the answer
is is relatively obvious. It's like
where your desires are. And that's
another thing. See, um there's that suta
that um I can't remember which one, but
there's a layman talking to the Buddha
and he said uh that well he was kind of
impressed uh with the with the Buddhist
teaching because he said like when he or
they as
householders hear about giving up
sensuality uh giving up
uh giving up
desires, giving up the um engagement
with the senses that feels
for him like a sudden abyss like a
precipice. It's that type of fear when
you hear like oh you got to give up um
the central pleasures of the
world. So, and that's another reason why
the the simile uh does not refer to the
painful feelings that a monk has to
endure because they do not necessarily
bring that as I said deeply existential
kind of threat that a person used to
sensuality would feel when they hear or
find out or even try to say no to their
desires in the beginning. So it and this
this layman was telling to the Buddha
like, "Oh, it's amazing that you know
you're teaching and the monks seem to be
enjoying doing it because when I hear
about giving sensuality, it just feels
like I'm just at the edge of a massive
abyss, a precipice. So you get like full
on that anxiety and and
panic. So that's where the battleground
is. Battleground is on the level of u
saying no to your sense desires keeping
keeping the lid on your actions uh and
you're going to experience you're going
to start experiencing anxiety doubt
mental pressure elephant will try to
make you you know let it run away allow
it to go
away and and that's really where the
training is so it's not even so much
about the sight sounds sounds of the
drums and so on it's about what they
invoke in the mind that's not trained.
So you can imagine imagine like you know
well through the course of our rebirth
we were all at some point fighting in
some war somewhere. So if you were to
imagine say you were with a some small
army sitting on top of some I don't know
in some valley in some on some land
somewhere and you just surrounded by the
sounds of enemies drums coming from the
mountains coming from everywhere else
and it's like you're going to feel
afraid because see there's lots of
implications in those sounds now coming
your way and uh but see it would be easier
way and uh but see it would be easier
then and I'm sure that what happens in
wars and these battles how they used to
be fought uh it would be a lot easier to
then just
charge or run away like okay if you can
run away you run away you can't run away
it would be easier to charge in the
battle even if it's the tenfold army
that's waiting for you than to stay
there and listen to the
drums that's the
point because that's unpleasant that
discomfort comes from inside comes from
that abyss and it's like and as I said I'm
abyss and it's like and as I said I'm
pretty sure that's what happens in wars
when when somebody gets too much on that
psychological level they just charge
they just charge with a knife against
the I don't know guns and so on because
it's easier than to stay on that level
you know you're going to die but at
least it will end that's that's what you
think at a time and this is the same
point see you start practicing the sense
restraint saying no to your sensual
desires I say that would have been
uninhibited beforehand or up to that
point. Well, you're going to feel like
your whole entire world now that's
around you is the world of the that
threat of that
desire. So even if it started through
like saying no to a specific thing,
specific object of your desire, it's
very quickly going to become that
allencompassing abyss. And that's the
training. That's the whole point. That's
why the virtue comes first. So that when
you get overwhelmed with doubt, with
everything else, I don't know what to
do. Well, you know what not to
do. But see, staying on that level even
when you know that it's a training, it's
something that you need to keep
reminding yourself
because it will be easier. Well, if if
say if you're not giving into
sensuality, that would be the easiest.
That's the least resistance option. But
say you would have built up enough um
determination, value, faith in the
teaching. So you are not giving in,
you're not breaking the precepts. But
then it does uh another there is a real
risk to go then too far to be like the
one who charges the the the the at the
drums to to end it. So you don't stay on
that level where that anxiety and doubt
persist. So it would be easier then to
say double down in your efforts. Say no
to more
things. Withdraw yourself even more.
Concentrate even
harder. Why? Because the the the sound
of the surrounding battle drums is
driving you
insane. But you realize the only true
way to deal with it, the only true way
for that elephant to be developed as
well is to stay with it. And that would
be the true, you know, warrior because
whether you charge at the at the battle
drums or you run away from them, uh, or
say you choose to, I don't know,
concentrate on your nostrils or watch
your sensations until you forget where
you are. Hypnotize yourself basically
into forgetting the drums. And then
you're seemingly peaceful. And then you
wake up. Then you come out of that
state. And then you still have to deal
with the drums. You still have to deal
with the mind that flinches in face of
the drums because you haven't addressed
it. But if you actually persevere on
that level, don't lose yourself in
level, don't lose yourself in
self-hypnotic
practices. Don't charge blindly to like
doubling down in efforts and self-
torment and so on. Don't revert back to
sensuality. The elephant will get used
to it will not flinch even if the the
drumming continues for three months.
like the elephant will be calm and then
you realize whatever happens after that
whether there is an actual uh battle
ensuing or no you already dealt with
it through training your mind on that
level it has already addressed the
battleground it has already addressed
the battle and the enemy whichever way
the battle goes it becomes secondary
becomes
unimportant so that kind of answers this
question as well. Is it still somewhat
possible to compose your mind before
training in the enduring of the five
objects? And as I said, if by that
composing you mean, you know, start uh
investing effort in um in your precepts
in sense restraint, then yes, it's
possible to compose your mind. But if by
compose your mind mean can you through
concentration practices speed up the process of
practices speed up the process of
getting used to the frightening battle
drums? No, not a chance. It takes you
away from it. As I said, you you
hypnotize yourself away. So, it's gone
and when you come back, it's still
waiting for you. So, it never addresses
the root issue, which is that the mind
flinches, falters in face of the abyss,
in face of saying no to
sensuality. And then um yeah, people
have asked like so why is au not being
worthy of offerings?
if he doesn't train in this way and um
as I like I think I guess again now by
now the answer should be obvious because
if there is no training in regard to
sight sound smell taste touches well
there is no training in the
dharma so the the answer is simple like
he's not worthy of offerings because
he's not the one practicing the dharma
um and consequently the one who is
training in regard to the senses is thus
training in samadei is thus training in
dhamma and that's why he is worthy of
offerings. So the unpleasantness of the
senses is what cannot be endured as the
name of the suta
says. And uh in a way yes but then in
another way no. So the unpleasantness of
the senses
u is what kind of makes you look of your
senses is what makes you look past
them because they're as as we spoke
before in our you know in other talks
how that inherent that resistance
towards your own sense bases they're
uncomfortable they're burden they're
exposure and because of that by default
underlying tendencies make you make you
look past
make you look elsewhere which is
obviously going to take you to the their
counterpart sides sounds melt touches.
So technically what you cannot
endure is the fear that arises on
account of removing the access to their
counterparts. And then obviously the
unpleasantness the inherent
unpleasantness of the senses is sure
fueling that fear even more. But
fundamentally even if you are say
trained if the elephant is trained and
there is no more fear or faltering in
regard to the sites touches they try to
trap you or pressure you uh you would be
feeling that
unpleasantness of the of your senses for
as long as the aggregates don't break
apart and um you don't even need to
think about specifically having to
endure it or something like that because
there is no more fear arising on account
of not being able to escape the
confinement of those senses through
engaging with uh sense
objects. So how is the second question
is how is aroused by a desirable object
to be understood? And yeah that's that's
again a good question. So what
constitutes arousal? Does does seeing agreeable
arousal? Does does seeing agreeable
things immediately mean desire is
there? How do you know where the line
is? Like you see something you
like. Does that mean oh so so sight of
that already means desire or is there
some space so to speak in between before
it becomes a
desire? Well it depends. Sometimes if
your desire if your behavior hasn't been
checked seeing it will immediately mean
a desire.
But if you would have been practicing
restraint, keeping the virtue, seeing
the um things that of the agreeable
nature, seeing, smelling, taste and
touching will not immediately give rise
to the mind of desire. Um and you will
be able to see that difference through
practicing of the sense restraint.
That's pretty much the purpose of it is
to to u highlight and pretty much expose
a difference between Yeah. That's which
is factually agreeable, factually
preferable. And then the thirst, the
desire, the pressure that overtakes the
mind. So aroused by a desirable object
refers to the mind being
overtaken towards its thirst towards
sight, sound, smell, taste, touches.
So the reason why this is important to
distinguish is because again you could
easily fall into as I said that doubling
down effort and just saying no twice as
much because you implicitly are blaming
sight sounds smell taste touches for
your desires for the
arousal and and if you keep keep doing
that you will keep overlooking the level
where the problem
is and is the underlying tendency of
fear displayed in the elephant somewhat
present in the big as well when facing
sense objects. Uh yeah certainly in the
beginning like
um
fear, anxiety, doubt pretty much the
five hindrances will be the five ways
then an untrained mind will keep trying
to get you to to flinch to falter to to
run away from the the the the drums that
are scaring you or run at them one way
or the other. it wants to make you act.
And that is all always kind of um
underneath all of that, it's always
going to be that fear and doubt. Um and
that's also like you could see the where
the the the power of faith would come in
like cuz you know sometimes you can
reason sometimes you can remind yourself
you know through the right mindfulness
that well this is staying on the right
level but sometimes none of that will be
heard by your own mind and then just out
of faith you just have to stay at that
level because as frightening as it is
it's the safest place to be running away
will probably get you killed because
you're surrounded. Running at it will
certainly get you killed even faster.
So, not neither running forward nor
running backward will at least give you
the most
time. But that means you do have to stay
on the level of that mental unease. And
that's far harder than, as I said, even
just charging in the battle with a with
a pocketk knife or something.